George Lardner Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
George Lardner Papers 1923-2005 1965-2001
Lardner, George
180,000 items
561 containers plus 1 oversize and 1 classified
225 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist and author. Writings, notes, interviews, correspondence, and research material including newspaper clippings, printed matter, reports, photographs, legal documents, financial records, and congressional hearing records and other government documents. Pertains chiefly to Lardner's career as a national news reporter for the Washington Post.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bush, George W. (George Walker), 1946-; Bush, George, 1924-2018.; Carter, Billy.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Church, Frank, 1924-1984.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Donovan, Raymond James, 1930-2021.; Flood, Daniel J.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Garrison, Jim, 1921-1992.; Gramm, Phil.; Hart, Gary, 1936-; Jordan, Hamilton.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Assassination.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968--Assassination.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968--Assassination.; Lardner family.; Lardner, George.; Lardner, Kristin, 1970-1992.; Lugar, Richard.; Meese, Edwin.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Nofzinger, Franklyn C.; North, Oliver.; Quayle, Dan, 1947-; Reagan, Ronald.; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998.; Wallach, E. Robert, 1934-; Weaver, Randy, 1948-
Organizations
Cointelpro.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; United States. Congress. House. Select Committee on Assassinations.; United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee to Study Governmental Operations with Respect to Intelligence Activities.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; United States. Freedom of Information Act.; United States. National Archives and Records Administration.; United States. National Security Agency.; Washington-Baltimore Newspaper Guild.; Wedtech (Firm)
Subjects
Abscam Bribery Scandal, 1980.; Abused women--Crimes against--United States.; American newspapers--Washington (D.C.); Assassination--United States.; Bombings--Oklahoma--Oklahoma City.; Bribery--United States.; Campaign funds--Corrupt practices--United States.; Conflict of interests--Political aspects--United States.; Conspiracy theories--United States.; Criminal justice, Administration of--United States.; Defense contracts--Corrupt practices--United States.; Domestic intelligence--United States.; Domestic terrorism--United States.; Elections--Corrupt practices--United States.; Electronic intelligence--United States.; Electronic surveillance--United States.; Espionage, American.; Espionage.; Family violence--Law and legislation--United States.; Government, Resistance to--United States.; Intelligence service--United States.; Internal security--United States.; Intervention (Federal government)--United States.; Investigative reporting--United States.; Iran-Contra Affair, 1985-1990.; Journalism--United States.; Labor unions--Corrupt practices--United States.; Lie detectors and detection--United States.; Mafia.; Military assistance, American--Iran.; Military assistance, American--Nicaragua.; Oklahoma City Federal Building Bombing, Oklahoma City, Okla., 1995.; Organized crime investigation--United States.; Personnel records--Access control--United States.; Political campaigns--Corrupt practices--United States.; Political campaigns--United States.; Political corruption--United States.; Political ethics--United States.; Presidents--United States--Archives.; Presidents--United States--Election.; Secret service--United States.; Spies--United States.; Stalking--Law and legislation--United States.; Terrorism.; Undercover operations--United States.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.; Wiretapping--United States.; Women--Violence against--United States.
Places
United States--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--21st century.
Titles
Washington post.
Occupations
Journalists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of George Lardner, journalist and author, was given to the Library of Congress by Lardner in 1999. Lardner made additional donations between 2000 and 2006.
Transfers
Sound recordings and video recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the George Lardner Papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division in advance of a research visit.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the Washington Post Historical Collection (see https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms019001).
National Security Classified Information
Government regulations control the use of national security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1934, Aug. 10 Born, New York, N.Y.
1951 1954 Part-time copy-editor, Bell Syndicate, New York, N.Y.
1956 A.B. degree, Marquette University, Milwaukee, Wis. Photoengraving apprentice, Williston Engraving, Milwaukee, Wis.
1956 1957 Part-time copyboy, Milwaukee Sentinel, Milwaukee, Wis.
1957 Married Rosemary Schalk
1957 1959 Reporter, Worcester Telegram, Worcester, Mass.
1959 1963 Reporter, Miami Herald, Miami, Fla.
1962 M.A. degree, Marquette University, Milwaukee, Wis.
1963 2004 Reporter, Washington Post, Washington, D.C.
1967 Byline award, Marquette University, Milwaukee, Wis
1977 American Bar Association certificate of merit
1991 2002 Board member, chairman, The Fund for Investigative Journalism
1993 Pulitzer Prize for series on the stalking and murder in Boston, Mass., of his daughter, Kristin Lardner
1995 Published The Stalking of Kristin: A Father Investigates the Murder of His Daughter (New York: Atlantic Monthly Press. 340 pp.)
Scope and Content Note
The papers of George Lardner (1934-2019) span the years 1923-2005 with the bulk of the material dating from 1965 to 2001. The collection focuses on Lardner's career as an investigative reporter with the Washington Post and extensively documents his research into a wide variety of national news stories. The papers are arranged into two parts described below.
Part I
Part I of the Lardner papers span the years 1923-1997, with the bulk of the material dating from 1965 to 1995 and documents his career as a reporter and as a commentator in other journals and magazines. Lardner maintained topical files that are organized as an alphabetical Subject File series comprising the majority of the papers. A small Miscellany series completes the collection.
The Subject File reflects the manner in which Lardner acquired, received, and pursued information and then developed his research into news stories. It includes Lardner's articles, correspondence, interviews, notes, and the research material he collected as documentary evidence. Research material includes newspaper and related clippings, reports, legal documents and trial records, government documents, some of which were obtained through Freedom of Information Act requests, congressional hearing records, photographs, and printed matter. Although Lardner's subject terms have been largely retained, personal names have been modified where necessary to conform to name authority standards of the Library of Congress.
Lardner's long tenure with the Washington Post allowed him to follow topics for many years, reporting from various angles as fresh information became available. Subjects branch into subcategories for ongoing stories of several years' duration, such as the court cases of the Iran-Contra Affair. In other instances, succeeding stories arise out of new lines of inquiry. Lardner's files on the Central Intelligence Agency, for example, contain material from twenty years of news gathering and reporting. Lardner's focus was on reform efforts and congressional oversight of intelligence activities, beginning with his coverage of investigations by the “Church Committee,” the United States Senate Select Committee to Study Government Operations with Respect to Intelligence Activities led by Senator Frank Church. Other intelligence-related subjects in the collection include spy cases, terrorism, the National Security Agency, and the Federal Bureau of Investigation, which cover, in particular, the COINTELPRO domestic intelligence program, wiretapping, electronic surveillance, use of lie detectors, and reform efforts.
Lardner's political investigations often concern corruption, wrongdoing, and conflicts of interest. His records of the Watergate Affair involve the trials, campaign funding scandals, especially the Milk Fund investigation, impeachment issues, and government and media access to Richard M. Nixon's recordings of conversations in the Oval Office. During the administration of Jimmy Carter, Lardner investigated William A. “Billy” Carter and Hamilton Jordan and reported on the “Floodgate” scandal centering on representative Daniel J. Flood of Pennsylvania and allegations of influence peddling, bribes, and Mafia connections. Abscam and Brilab files cover federal law enforcement “sting” operations.
During the Ronald Reagan administration, Lardner's files concern a number of investigations, usually led by special prosecutors. Extensive files are available for the investigations of Labor Secretary Raymond Donovan. Material concerning the Wedtech investigation relates to improper influence to gain military contracts and is filed under the company name, Wedtech, with related material filed under Franklyn C. “Lyn” Nofzinger, Edwin Meese, and E. Robert Wallach. Files on Oliver North and the Iran-Contra Affair concern the sale of arms to Iran in exchange for hostages and the diversion of money from that sale to the Contras in Nicaragua. Iran-Contra investigations continued into the George Bush administration.
Political assassinations are a prominent feature of Lardner's files, especially the assassination of John F. Kennedy. The Kennedy file includes material on Jim Garrison's prosecution in 1967 of various figures in New Orleans. Lardner later obtained documents from the Central Intelligence Agency, Federal Bureau of Investigation, and other government agencies through the Freedom of Information Act and reported on developments in many conspiracy theories. He also covered the investigation of Kennedy's assassination by the United States House of Representatives Select Committee on Assassinations and, to a lesser extent, the committee's investigation of the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr.
Political election campaigns are a minor subject in the collection. Presidential campaign files include coverage for some of the primaries in 1972 and 1976. Files on campaign spending concern the 1984 presidential race. Lardner's files include profiles he wrote of presidential candidates Frank Church, Phil Gramm, Gary Hart, Dan Quayle, Edward Moore Kennedy, Richard Lugar, and George C. Wallace.
Lardner wrote a series of articles on the Freedom of Information Act and followed the subject for some time, developing related stories concerning presidential papers administered by the National Archives and Records Administration. Other significant files include those for Ruby Ridge and Oklahoma City that concern confrontations of private citizens with federal law enforcement agencies. Ruby Ridge files cover a federal siege and shoot-out at the Randy Weaver home near Ruby Ridge, Idaho. The Oklahoma City files concern the bombing of a federal building in the city, with related material filed under militias. Files on the Mafia are mostly related to alleged political ties and corruption of unions.
Material in the Miscellany series on the Washington-Baltimore Newspaper Guild and Lardner's employment by the Washington Post Company document aspects of the working life of journalists.
Part II
Part II of the Lardner papers span the years 1956-2005, with the majority concentrated in the period between 1990 and 2001. In part, these papers supplement files in Part I and pertain to some of Lardner’s earlier assignments in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s as a reporter covering national news for the Washington Post. The majority of Part II reflects later portions of Lardner’s career at the Washington Post not represented in Part I and documents his assignments from the 1990s and early 2000s. The arrangement of the papers in Part II mirror that of Part I and are organized into the following series: Subject File and Miscellany.
Similar to the Subject File in Part I, the Subject File in Part II reflects the manner in which Lardner acquired, received, and pursued information and then developed his research into news stories. The series includes Lardner's articles, correspondence, interviews, notes, and the research material he collected as documentary evidence. Research material includes newspaper clippings, reports, legal documents and trial records, government documents, some of which were obtained through Freedom of Information Act requests, congressional hearing records, photographs, and printed matter. Lardner's subject terms and headings have been largely retained and represent the way he thought about and categorized his research. The organization of these papers reflect the high degree of interconnectedness often apparent in current events and news stories, with people, locations, and subjects appearing in various places across the collection.
Many of the earlier files in Part II complement those in Part I and provide continuation of Lardner’s many investigations into intelligence agencies and policies, political corruption, and political assassinations. Prominent investigations continued in Part II include the Iran-Contra Affair, Labor Secretary Raymond Donovan, improper influence to gain military contracts by Wedtech, the assassination of Robert F. Kennedy, among other topics. Political election campaigns in 1968, 1970, 1972, 1976, and 1984 also complement Part I, especially the campaigns of George C. Wallace.
The majority of the Subject File reflects the stories Lardner followed in the later portion of his career at the Washington Post in the 1990s and early 2000s. These stories focus in large part on political figures and controversies and extensively chronicle the Bill Clinton and George W. Bush administrations. Lardner’s investigations into the Clinton administration are varied and include allegations of Chinese influence and illegal fund raising tactics in the 1996 presidential election and improper access to personnel security-clearance documents in a controversy referred to as “Filegate.” Many of the records pertaining to George W. Bush reflect research into his life and activities before being elected president in 2000. A significant portion of files chronicle Lardner’s research into the assassination of John F. Kennedy for a thirtieth anniversary special television documentary titled Who Killed JFK: The Final Chapter?
Documents related to domestic violence, stalking laws, and the murder of Lardner’s daughter, Kristin, in 1992 are represented to a lesser extent, but mark an important aspect of Part II of these papers. Notes, speech transcripts, and correspondence with readers document Lardner’s work to expose the shortcomings of the criminal justice system to protect victims of stalking and domestic violence and to advocate for passage of the Violence Against Women Act. Research files include interview notes, statistics, and printed matter.
The Miscellany series chronicles Lardner’s life apart from his investigative work and includes correspondence with his wife, Rosemary, and children, correspondence related to his involvement with the Fund for Investigative Journalism, and some writing projects. General correspondence with colleagues from the Washington Post and reader responses to some of Lardner's articles are contained in this series, as is Washington Post material that is administrative in nature, such as expense reports and contact lists.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged in two parts composed of six series:
Part I
Subject File, 1923-1997
Miscellany, 1963-1995
Oversize, 1980
National Security Classified Information, 1961-1963
Part II
Subject File, 1959-2005
Miscellany, 1956-2001
Container List
- Part I: Subject File, 1923-1997 (Box 1-285)
  Writings, notes, interviews, correspondence, and research material including newspaper clippings, printed matter, reports, photographs, legal documents, financial records, congressional hearing records, and other government documents.
  Arranged alphabetically by the subject of the stories Lardner reported and investigated and chronologically thereunder.
  - Abscam operation (Box 1)
    - Articles, undated
    - Notes, 1980, undated
    - Research material, 1980, (2 folders)
  - Afghanistan, 1983
  - Anderson, Kevin E.
    - Correspondence, 1990
    - Notes, 1990
    - Research material
      - Legal documents, 1987-1989
      - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1986-1990, undated, (2 folders)
  - Angola
    - Articles, 1990
    - Notes, 1990, undated
    - Research material, 1989-1990, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Aqaba oil pipeline See Containers 121-123, Iraqi pipeline
  - Aspin, James, 1981-1986
  - Bacon, Leslie (U.S. Capitol bombing)
    - Articles and correspondence, 1970-1971, undated
    - Interviews, undated
    - Notes
      - Miscellaneous, 1970, undated
      - Notebooks, undated
    - Research material
      - Legal documents, 1971, undated
      - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1971, undated
  - Bank of Credit and Commerce International (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and notes, 1991
    - Research material
      - Miscellaneous, 1989-1991
      - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1991, undated
      - Report, 1991
  - Bentsen, Lloyd M.
    - Articles and interviews, 1988, undated
    - Correspondence, 1988
    - Notes, 1988, undated, (2 folders)
    - Research material (Box 4)
      - Jimmy Carter Library, Atlanta, Ga., 1976-1988, undated, (2 folders)
      - Legal documents, 1961, 1970
      - Lyndon B. Johnson Library, Austin, Tex., 1953-1988, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1957-1967, 1975-1978, (2 folders)
      - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1950, 1970-1989, undated, (4 folders)
  - Brian, Earl W., 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - Brilab operation
    - Articles, 1980
    - Notes, 1977-1980, undated
    - Research material
      - Legal documents, 1979
      - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1978-1981, undated, (3 folders)
  - Brown, Ronald H., 1973-1980
  - Campaign funds, congressional elections, 1965-1966
  - Campaign spending, 1984 national election campaigns See also Containers 99-104, Hart, Gary
    - Congressional races in California, Connecticut, and Oklahoma, 1984
    - Federal Election Commission
      - Advisory opinions, 1984
      - Congressional campaign spending report, 1983-1984
      - Political Action Committee spending reports, 1983-1984
    - Fund for a Conservative Majority, 1983-1984, undated (Box 6)
    - Hart, Gary
      - Articles, interviews, and notes, 1983-1984
      - Research material, 1954, 1983-1984, (2 folders)
    - Illinois senate race, 1983-1984
    - Independents for Ronald Reagan, 1984
    - Miscellany, 1984
    - Mondale, Walter
      - Delegate committees
        - Articles, 1984
        - Interviews and notes, 1984
        - Research material (Box 7)
          - Federal Election Commission
            - Filings, 1984
              - Florida
              - Maryland
              - Miscellaneous states, (2 folders)
              - New York
              - Pennsylvania
            - Indexes and lists, 1983-1984
          - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1983-1984, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1983-1984
    - National Congressional Club, 1984 (Box 8)
    - National Conservative Political Action Committee
      - Disputes before the Federal Election Commission, 1984, (3 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1984, undated
      - Reports on receipts and disbursements, 1984
    - National Republican Congressional Committee, 1984
    - National Republican Senatorial Committee, 1984
    - Political action committees, general, 1983-1985, (2 folders)
    - Reagan-Bush reelection campaign (Box 9)
      - Federal Election Commission, selected list of receipts and expenditures, 1980 See Oversize
      - General Election Committee, 1984
      - Miscellaneous support groups, 1980-1984, undated
      - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1975, 1984, undated
    - Republican National Committee, 1984
    - Ruff Political Action Committee, 1984
  - “Capital Column,” 1977
  - Carter, William A. ("Billy")
    - Articles, 1980-1981, undated
    - Correspondence, 1980, undated
    - Interviews, 1980, undated
    - Notes, 1980-1982, undated, (5 folders)
    - Research material (Box 10)
      - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1979-1980, undated
      - Freedom of Information Act requests, 1980-1989, undated
      - Justice Department, report, 1981, undated
      - Legal documents
        - Exhibits, 1979-1980, (2 folders)
        - General, 1979-1980, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1979-1980, undated
      - Newspaper clippings and related material
        - 1977-1979
        - 1980
          - Feb.-May
          - July-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 11)
        - 1981, undated
      - Resolution of inquiry, 1980, undated (Box 12)
      - Senate Judiciary Committee
        - General, 1980, undated, (3 folders)
        - Notes, 1980, undated, (5 folders)
        - Report of the committee, 1980 (Box 13)
        - Report of the president, 1980
  - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA)
    - Afghanistan, 1985
    - Agee, Philip
      - Article, interviews, and notes, 1977-1980
      - Research material
        - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1975-1981
        - Legal documents, 1980-1981, (2 folders)
    - Airlie Foundation, 1973-1977, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Angola, 1978-1981, undated
    - Angleton, James, 1977-1981
    - Arrow Air, 1984-1986, undated
    - Assassination plots (Box 15)
      - Correspondence and interviews, 1975, undated
      - Notes, undated
      - Research material, 1961, 1971-1975, undated
    - Budget, 1977-1979, undated
    - Butterfield, Alexander, and executive branch “infiltration,” 1974-1975, undated, (2 folders)
    - Casey, William J.
      - Confirmation hearings as director
        - Articles and notes, 1980-1981, undated
        - Research material, 1972-1981, undated, (2 folders)
      - Finances (Box 16)
        - Articles, interviews, and notes, 1981-1983
        - Research material
          - Government documents, 1981-1982
          - Legal documents and reports, numerical file, 1981-1984, (5 folders)
          - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1981-1983
      - Hugel, Max, resignation as deputy director of clandestine operations (Box 17)
        - Articles, 1981
        - Interviews and notes, 1981, undated
        - Research material
          - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1979-1981, undated
          - Transcripts of audiotapes, 1981, undated
      - Miscellany
        - Articles and notes, 1982-1983, undated
        - Newspaper clippings and related material, 1981-1986
      - Securities and Exchange Commission chairmanship, 1971-1974, 1980, undated
      - Senate inquiry
        - Articles, 1981, undated
        - Interviews and notes, 1981, undated, (2 folders)
        - Research material
          - Casey responses and support, 1981
          - Congressional press releases, 1981